you know I'll just share this because I
the audience might find it interesting
doing science is a non-trivial process
if you want to really do good science
comprehensively and most of what we
think of as science is not comprehensive
so we can do something like you know
phase three if they approval clinical
trials on a statin to show that it does
lower LDL that doesn't mean that that
it's actually good for health right it
means that it was good for that metric
and so of course we'll see Vioxx and
premarin and so many drugs get pulled
from the market after tens of thousands
of people died or that we just deal with
the side effects and maybe we say the
benefits are worth the side effects but
we're not looking at things that could
have been comprehensively much better
had we gone up line and so to do science
means well which metrics do you study
which metrics are going to be affected
maybe millions right we're only going to
look at a few so we're doing like with
all of our ingredients and quality right
now you know Dan and I are working
together on doing meta analyses and we
have some other people on the team doing
meta analyses of all the ingredients and
if we just look at all of this formal
kind of scientific literature we might
have several hundred studies per
ingredients that looked at different
metrics and different kinds of audiences
what was done in sick populations are in
healthy or in young or an older male or
female and there's a actually making
sense of that as non-trivial and then
you have stuff like what Chinese
medicine found worked empirically for
5000 years but we don't have formal
science on it yet but we have a huge
apocrypha of data or what say
bodybuilders or elite athletes or
different groups kind of through self
experimentation or quantified self have
found has worked and so I almost think
of science as too narrow a way of
thinking about what we need to do we
think we're thinking of it as
sense-making
how do we actually take all of the data
the confidence margins on the data what
part of it it looks at and put it all
together and really make sense of health
and well-being and that's really what we
like I'd say that's at the core of what
neural hackers focused on over the next
little bit is how do we scale our
capacity to do sense making in
well-being so that we really know what
works what doesn't work what does work
even mean what works at the expense of
what what could work comprehensively
better across the space of meaningful
health
interventions and practices that's one
of the things that drew me to neuro
hacker in the first place was you know
I'd been using a bunch of cognitive
nootropic enhancement supplementation
for years and in my clients and you know
you got about a 50/50 mix of responses I
mean I actually was developing my own
powder for a while but I was following a
lot of the same rules that all these
other companies did is I would find a
study that said hey this ingredient
works really well for this outcome and
this ingredient works really well for
this outcome well great so I've put in
ten ingredients that work on ten
different processes but never really
paid attention to the interaction of
each of those with each other right and
that number one impressed me with the
ingredients research done on neuro
hacker but more so was the fact that I
was getting over ninety five percent of
my clients taking the the qualia were
reporting positive outcomes which you
know prior to that it was about 50/50 of
people saying hey this stuff really
worked or I didn't feel anything
different with it and when I'm seeing
this this really high response rate I
mean that's what prompted me to reach
out to you guys in the first place and
want to get an interview with you to
talk about the product because it just
blew me away with what I was hearing
from subjective feedback from from my
clients and for the people who are
listening you know I think that what we
are doing here is barely scratching at
the surface of what needs to happen and
what we want to do when you think about
the fact that to take a pharmaceutical
drug through FDA trials is in the
vicinity of a billion dollars you've
gotten down to about a half a billion
dollars for some some are still more
than that but then when you factor all
the ones that fail and phase one or
phase two you know trials it might be
well over a billion dollars total costs
for those that make it and that doesn't
mean that they actually cure anything
they're mostly symptomatic treatment
mostly with side effects
and it doesn't even mean that they're
actually better than nothing at all five
years down the road when we end up
pulling you know and some of them get
pulled like there are a few that are
great antibiotics have had a very useful
application that's been limited of
course they've also had huge blowback
wrongly utilized the new category of
immuno oncology is pretty awesome but
almost everything in cancer therapy up
till this point was pretty sub awesome
but you know part of why we don't know
how to deal with autoimmune disease when
we don't know how to deal with
neurodegenerative disease when I deal
with cancer well is if the cause isn't
acute and obvious and it's more complex
it's a hard thing to figure out and so
there's a whole different process
medicine has to take I won't go down
this road too far cuz then I'll do a
whole podcast on this sometime but in
the same way that understanding all the
complex causation feeding into a disease
is there's a lot involved to understand
the effect of chemistry on the body and
especially mixed chemistry's on the body
is actually fairly involved there's a
lot of things to study so we paid as
much attention as we could to thinking
through whole pathways the entire
acetylcholine regulation pathway the
whole dopamine regulation pathway and
where the rate limiting factors would be
and if we open that up what are all the
pathways that are known of that would be
affected what the next rate limiter is
what would be where might there be
toxicity how do we make sure that
doesn't happen but then how to actually
assess all that further right like so
we're doing trials then and they're
working on clinical trials but but
clinical trials really just say does
this thing do something on a finite set
of metrics more than the placebo does
that doesn't say what is everything
happening right so the fact that we
think of clinical trials is a gold
standard so if there's a bell curve of
effect why did these people get great
effects and these people got shitty
effects and that was only on whatever
metrics what about the gazillion other
metrics and what about the longer-term
metrics and so how do we create much
more comprehensive methods of
sense-making systems as complex as human
biology this is this is really at the
heart of our mission here I digress you
know I think we were coming up on with
all the metrics we're starting to look
at we're coming up on a really exciting
time and
in the spire Information Age mean with
the quantified self stuff and everybody
wearing it and contributing their
genetic data and their lab work and and
all of this information into the cloud
into these bioinformatics systems I
think we're truly starting to I mean
we're we're really just scratching the
surface of what what the potential is
going to be it's exciting
definitely so we might do in a whole
podcast on AI and bioinformatics in the
future of diagnosis to watch the full
episode or to subscribe to the podcast
click the link in the description or
visit us at neuro hacker comm slash
collective insights
[Music]
you